Today's דף *daf* is ס"ד *Samech Dalet*, 64, and we pick up
at the very bottom of ס"ג עמוד ב B, *Samech Gimmel Amud
Bet* and we are talking about the issue of again about what
type of clothes can be worn on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, except here
we've turned a little into the discussion of טומאה tumah וטהרה *Tumah
ve-Taharah* which always seems to be an accompanying discussion. So we pick
up on the bottom of ס"ג עמוד ב *Samech Gimmel Amud Bet*.
Let's start from תנו רבנן Tanoo rabanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*, six lines from
the bottom, right after the little circle, מאי בגד *Mai Beged*. תנו
רבנן Tanoo rabanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*: אריג areg. כל שהוא טמא tamei. *Arig
kol shehu tamei*. A woven piece of clothing, even the smallest size,
is טמא tamei. *tamei*. Again, normally we say three by three fingers,
sometimes three by three טפחים *tefachim* because as it's explained the difference
is that that's when you have some remnant of a larger clothing.
This is when the entire thing was made to be a very
small type of a thing, like maybe a little wrap around the
finger or something, whatever it was. So therefore, even the smallest size.
ותכשיט כל שהוא טמא tamei *Ve-tashchit kol shehu tamei*, or an ornament,
the smallest size, maybe something made out of metal or whatever, wood,
not cloth, not like a weave, but nevertheless even a small ornament
is טמא tamei? *tamei*. אריג ותכשיט כל שהוא טמא tamei? *Arig ve-tashchit
kol shehu tamei*. Let's say it's a combination, you know, maybe I
don't know it's a brooch that has like a woven string that
you attach on. So also if it's some combination of it's also
טמא tamei *tamei*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says if you said כל שהוא
*kol shehu* is טמא tamei *tamei*, then obviously if it's combination it's
טמא tamei *tamei* because each component has a כל שהוא *kol shehu*.
So you could have said that no, each component is not a
thing in itself, it's only half of a thing, but תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot*'s answer is that כל שהוא *kol shehu* there's even a minimum
size to a כל שהוא *kol shehu*. Not everything is a כל
שהוא *kol shehu*. So you have something that's a combination of an
ornament and a weave, each one is a half of a כל
שהוא *kol shehu* and combined they're a כל שהוא *kol shehu*, that
also is טמא tamei *tamei*. That's the way תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* reads
it. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מוסיף שק sak על
הבגד *mosif sak al ha-beged*, a sackcloth which is made from goat's
hair is more strict than a normal type of a garment, מוסיף
שק sak על הבגד שטמא משום אריג *mosif sak al ha-beged she-tamei
mishum arig* that it is טמא tamei. *tamei* because of woven materials,
which is a little funny because a garment is also טמא tamei.
*tamei* because of woven materials. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does with this. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*: אריג כל שהוא טמא
tamei? מאו בגד *Arig kol shehu tamei me-o beged*. Here is the
source of this ברייתא Baraita *braita*, the biblical source. A small woven
thing is טמא tamei. *tamei* from the verse we quoted before, או
o, בגד *o beged*, says by שרצים sheratzim *shratzim*, by the things
that touch a dead rodent, it says or a garment, so the
or is an extra word and it means even something that's a
tiny garment, even a כל שהוא *kol shehu*. תכשיט כל שהוא טמא
tamei *Tashchit kol shehu tamei*, a small type of a jewelry is
טמא tamei *tamei* מציץ *me-tzitz*, from ציץ *tzitz* like we said yesterday
that the ציץ *tzitz* was טמא tamei *tamei*, of course why we
learn from there כל שהוא *kol shehu* since the ציץ *tzitz* was
pretty big, I don't know, but that's what we're learning. אריג ותכשיט
כל שהוא טמא tamei *Arig ve-tashchit kol shehu tamei*, how do you
know a combination of the two is טמא tamei, *tamei*? מכל כלי
מעשה *mi-kol kli ma'aseh*, because the verse says by מדין Midian, *Midian*,
it says that they took all this booty and it says כל
כלי מעשה *kol kli ma'aseh*, all articles that were used for purpose.
So כל כלי *kol kli*, all articles, includes even some hybrid כלי
*kli* is also טמא tamei *tamei*. אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לרבא *Amar
lei hahu me-rabbanan le-Rava*, so one of the rabbis said to רבא
*Rava*, אהו במדין כתיב *ahu be-Midian ktiv*, that's written by מדין Midian.
*Midian*. Now why is that a problem that it's written by מדין
*Midian*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that מדין *Midian* the story was
that they came in contact with the war with dead bodies. So
even though it's טמא tamei *tamei* because of purposes of טומאת מת
meit. *tumat meit*, that's maybe a stricter category and maybe you can't
apply it to lighter טומאות tumos *tumot*. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says
that maybe it's not even about טומאה tumah *tumah* at all, that's
talking about the booty they got from מדין *Midian*. How do you
know that it refers to actual laws of טומאה tumah. *tumah*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר ליה *amar lei*, גמר כלי כלי
מהתם גזירה שוה gezeira shava. *gamar kli kli me-hatam gezeirah shavah*. By
the dead rodent it says כלי *kli*, by מדין *Midian* it says
כלי *kli*, so since by מדין *Midian* was there by מת meis
*meit* or just by the booty, כלי *kli* includes any vessel, even
some hybrid vessel, also by the טומאה tumah, *tumah* of dead rodent.
Okay, so that's where we know that these different types of things,
jewelry and even small garments and sackcloth is טמא tamei, *tamei*. But
now we are going to further analyze the last line of the
ברייתא braita, *braita* which was a little curious. מוסיף שק sak, על
הבגד שטמא משום אריג *mosif sak al ha-beged she-tamei mishum arig*, the
sackcloth is more strict or you know more than a normal garment,
that it is טמא tamei *tamei* because of the category of woven
objects. So the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* says אטו *atu*, what do you
mean? בגד לאו אריג הוא *beged lav arig hu*? A normal garment
isn't woven? A sackcloth is טמא *tamei* because of woven garments, more
than a בגד *beged*. בגד *beged* is your classic woven garment. So
the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* says הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, this is what
it means: מוסיף שק sak, על הבגד אף על פי שאינו אריג
טמא *mosif sak al ha-beged af al pi she-eino arig tamei*. So
a sackcloth isn't woven, so meaning it's in the category of a
type of a garment even though it's not woven. So it's טמא
*tamei*. משום אריג without being אריג. It's treated as if it's a
woven garment without being woven. Apparently they would make, I don't know,
I didn't check Wikipedia last night, but apparently they make things out
of goat's hair with doing more like a twining and, you know,
and whatever, it's not your classic type of a weaving of various
threads. So even though the sackcloth is not made out of is
not an actual weave, it nevertheless is טמא.
I'm always reminded of that I have to just say that of
this movie, My Cousin Vinny. Anybody ever see that? What a great
movie. Anyway, so the guy, the lawyer comes in once and the
judge tells him like he has to wear a suit. So the
next time he comes in with a suit made out of leather.
So he says, I would like next time a suit made out
of some type of cloth, you know, something woven. All right. So
anyway, so that's it. So a sackcloth might be a garment but
it's not exactly woven, but even so it is טמא. So the
גמרא Gmara says,
okay. So למאי חזי, l'mai chazi, so what do you would you
use שק sak, with without being fully woven? Maybe actually, not exactly
like I said, maybe that a normal שק sak garment would be,
you know, a sackcloth garment would be woven. But how would you
use a type of a, you know, goat's hair which was not
really woven? What would you use it for? So אמר רבי יוחנן
שכן עני קולע שלוש נימין ותולה בצואר בתו Amar Rabbi Yochanan sheken
ani kolea shalosh nimin v'tola b'tzavar bito that a poor person would
take three strings of goat's hair, twist them together, make like a
type of a, you know, braided string, and put it as a
type of a necklace, an inexpensive necklace. So therefore even though it's
not woven, it's just twisted goat's hair, that also counts, that's also
in the category. Okay. תנו רבנן, our Rabbis taught. שק, sak now
we're going to focus on this idea that sackcloth, again made out
of goat's hair, is טמא whether woven, maybe as a garment, whether
even twisted together. תנו רבנן, so our Rabbis taught, שק, sak. a
sackcloth. אין לי אלא שק, ein li ela sak, I only know
sackcloth. מנין לרבות את הקילקלי ואת החבק? minayin l'rabot et hakilkali v'et
hachavak? How do I know even these other things which are not
like full garments but קילקלי kilkali and חבק chavak which are רש"י
Rashi says that these are things that you would do for a
horse. I don't know how does the Steinsaltz or Artscroll translate
this? A breast strap and a girth? A breast... right, so different
types of, types of like, you know, straps that you would use
for horses. Okay. So how would you, how do you know that
even these types of things are included, are טמא? I mean they're
made out of goat's hair but also they're not made for human
clothing, they're made for horses. So the גמרא Gmara says תלמוד לומר
או שק. Talmud lomar o sak. So the extra או, o the
same way before we included even small sizes, here we're including things
made out of these goat's hair even if they're made for horses,
some type of a belt around the horses. יכול שאני ארבה את
החבלים ואת המשיחות? yachol she'ani arbeh et hachavalim v'et hameshichot? Maybe I
would come to include, you know, even other types of ropes? So
רש"י Rashi says that these types of ropes are made more for
measuring and the more important point is that they're not even twisted.
Meaning they're maybe like straight strings but, you know, the other thing
we said might not be woven, but at least the strings were
twisted together. This is not even in any way sort of spun
or twisted. So maybe but even those are included? So it says
תלמוד לומר שק. Talmud lomar sak. No, it has to be somewhat
like sackcloth. מה שק טווי ואריג אף כל טווי ואריג. ma sak
tavui v'arig af kol tavui v'arig. The same way sackcloth is twisted
and woven, so it has to be twisted and woven. Now we
learned before it didn't have to be woven, but at least it
has to be twisted. And presumably these are neither twisted nor woven
and therefore that does not, that would not be included. But something
other that was just twisted, whether like a little, you know, necklace
or something for the horses, that would be included. So now the
גמרא Gemara goes, so now the ברייתא goes on. הרי הוא אומר
במת, harei hu omer b'meit, so that it says by a dead
body, וכל כלי עור וכל מעשה עזים. v'chol kli or v'chol ma'aseh
izim. So the idea it says שק, sak, sackcloth, that was by
a dead rodent. How about by a corpse, a human body? What
does it make טמא? So there the verse says anything out of
leather and anything made out of goat's hair. וכל מעשה עזים תתחטאו,
v'chol ma'aseh izim titchata'u, you have to purify. So what is כל
מעשה עזים? kol ma'aseh izim? Anything made out of goat's hair? לרבות
את הקילקלי ואת החבק. l'rabot et hakilkali v'et hachavak. This comes to
include even this קילקלי kilkali and חבק, chavak, even this type of
a goat's hair strap made for
a horse. יכול שאני ארבה
את החבלים ואת המשיחות? yachol she'ani arbeh et hachavalim v'et hameshichot? Same
question. So it's the exact same issue which we discussed by a
dead rodent, now we're discussing by a corpse. We have different verses.
By the dead rodent the verse was או שק, o sak, so
שק on the one hand was limiting, not these types of ropes
that are not twisted. או o was including even something that is
just twisted not woven made for the horses. How do you do
the same discussion by the dead body, by the corpse? So there
it says כל מעשה עזים. kol ma'aseh izim. That's an inclusive
word. Even something like this קילקלאי kilklai and חבקה, chavaka, even something
that's just twisted. But how do you know to exclude the other
category of things which are not twisted, which are but are still
made out of goat's hair? So יכול שאני מרבה את החבלים ואת
המשיחות, yachol she'ani marbeh et hachavalim v'et hamshichot, maybe I would include
even these measuring ropes? ודינו, v'dino, and it makes sense to include
them, rather it makes sense to let's say exclude them to follow
the pattern of what we learned by the dead rodent. טימא בשרץ
וטימא במת. tima b'sheretz v'tima b'meit. It said that these type of
goat's hair things are tamei with a dead rodent and they're tamei
with a dead body. מה כשטימא בשרץ לא טימא אלא טווי ואריג,
mah k'she-tima b'sheretz lo tima ella tavui v'arig, so what we just
learned from או שק, o sak, this או o, being inclusive, the
שק being somewhat limiting, that when things become tamei by a dead
rodent, it requires that that thing made out of goat's hair be
both twisted or woven, but
if it's neither twisted nor woven, not. So by analogy I'll say
אף כשטימא במת לא טימא אלא טווי ואריג. af k'she-tima b'meit lo
tima ella tavui v'arig. So maybe also it's only if it's twisted
or woven, but not if it's not. So here's the problem. The
problem is that by a dead rodent we have an inclusive word
and an exclusive word. The inclusive word is או, the exclusive word
is שק. It has to be somewhat like sackcloth. So that gets
us to the middle position we're looking for, that straps that are
twisted, yes, are tamei, straps that are not twisted, ropes that are
untwisted and unwoven, are not tamei. By the dead body we only
have an inclusive word, כל מעשה עזים. kol ma'aseh izim. How do
we know to exclude that category of חבלים ומשיחות, chavalim u'mshichot, things
made out of goat's hair that are not twisted? It doesn't seem
to be based on any word when it's talking about a dead
body. So we're arguing, well, let's do it by analogy to the
dead rodent. There we make the split between two different types of
garments made out of goat's hair. Let's make the split by dead
bodies as well. So the Baraita goes on and says the following.
It says הין, hen, which is yes but sometimes it means no.
הין, hen, is that really true? Yeah, it is. I'm sorry, I'm
at a loss for words today. This famous story they say about
this guy Morgenbesser, Sidney Morgenbesser, somebody at this philosopher from Columbia University,
anyway he was like this great with these one liners. So he
was at a conference once and somebody got up and said it's
very strange, like a double negative makes a positive, but a double
positive doesn't make a negative. So he said הין הין. hen hen.
So anyway, so here the Gemara says yes but it means no.
הין, hen, is that really true that you can make the analogy
from a dead body, from a dead rodent? אם היקל בטומאת שרץ,
im heikel b'tumat sheretz, maybe the Torah is being lenient by the
rodent's case and saying not all things, not all goat's hair things
are tamei? Why? Because it's a rodent, it's a more lenient category.
שיקלה, she-kalla, it's more lenient. It's only a one-day tumah, not a
seven-day tumah. So okay, so it excludes certain types of garments. ניקל
בטומאת המת, neikel b'tumat hameit, does that make you think that we
can be lenient by dead bodies? שהיא חמורה, shehi chamura, which is
a much stricter category? So just because you have this split of
different garments by the dead rodents doesn't mean you're going to have
it by the dead bodies. So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so you
can't learn it out from the rodent. So where do you
learn it
out from? בגד ועור. beged v'or. בגד ועור לגזירה שוה. beged v'or
l'gezeira shava. So we learn it out
from somewhere else. By the dead bodies it says that if something
is a garment or something of leather it becomes tamei and it
says it elsewhere. Where does it say it elsewhere? נאמר בגד ועור
בשרץ ונאמר בגד ועור במת. ne'emar beged v'or b'sheretz v'ne'emar beged v'or
b'meit. It says it by the rodent and it says it by
the dead body. מה בגד ועור האמור בשרץ לא טימא אלא טווי
ואריג, mah beged v'or ha'amur b'sheretz lo tima ella tavui v'arig, the
same way that we know by rodents when you're dealing with different
garments of cloth or of leather, it's only when it is at
least cloth garments are only twisted or woven, אף בגד ועור האמור
במת לא טימא אלא טווי ואריג, af beged v'or ha'amur b'meit lo
tima ella tavui v'arig, it is only twisted or woven. So meaning
you can't learn it by analogy. If you're learning it by analogy,
an analogy is easy to challenge because if the cases are not
exactly analogous you can't make the analogy. So just because there's the
split by rodents doesn't mean the split is true by dead bodies.
But rather learn it by a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah. is a big equal sign. It's not an analogy, it's
not that it's parallel, it's just apply one category to the other.
So since you have the words בגד ועור beged v'or in both
cases, you're allowed to apply what we know from שרץ, sheretz, from
rodents, to the category of מת. meis So that's how we know
this difference between two different type of goat's hair garments. So the
Gemara says אלא מעתה מה בגד ועור, ela me'atah mah beged v'or,
now that we're saying that we can go in the reverse order
as well. ומה בגד ועור האמור במת טימא כל מעשה עזים, u'mah
beged v'or ha'amur b'meit tima kol ma'aseh izim, now by the verse
by the dead body it says כל מעשה עזים, kol ma'aseh izim,
anything made out of goat's hair. By the verse by the rodent
it only said שק, sackcloth. So anything out of goat's hair is
more inclusive. So now we'll use that to apply back to the
dead rodent. and meant to be more inclusive. So the same way
there it's anything made out of goat's hair, הבגד והעור או מה
בשרץ טימא כל מעשה עזים. Habeged veha'or o mah basheretz tima kol
ma'aseh izim. So therefore also it is more inclusive. Doesn't tell you
exactly what it's including, but now he's got this big equal sign
working. So goat's hair in general yes, but certain things are excluded
when they're not woven or they're twist or twisted. So now the
Beraita goes on, אין לי אלא דבר הבא מן העזים. Ein li
ela davar haba min ha'izim. So far you've included goat's hair. Okay,
and we know wool type of things, wool and linen that's obviously
included. But מנין לרבות דבר הבא מזנב הסוס ומזנב הפרה? Minayin lerabot
davar haba mizanav hasus umizanav haparah? How do I know about things
that are come from the tail of a horse or the tail
of a cow? So it's similar to like goat's hair in the
sense that it's hairs, it's not wool, right? It's like hairs of
the head. So how do I know that those are included in
the goat's hair category? So תלמוד לומר או שק. Talmud lomar o
sak. Go back to the rodents. It says the word O or
sackcloth, which is coming to be inclusive, so it includes anything like
sackcloth, anything out of other hairs as well, not just goat hairs,
even cow hairs. Why weren't the ropes then tamei? Because they're not
twisted. There's one question about what is the material you're using. Are
you using wool, are you using linen, are you using animal hair?
So animal hair is not just goat hair, it's other animal hair.
So that we learn from the O. But the one thing we
exclude from the word Sak is is that if it's just a
straight string, a straight hair, no, it's got to take multiple hairs
and twist them together and make it somewhat like you make normal
fabric. Apparently, I don't know the exact metzius, but apparently some ropes
the Gemara said yes, but it was excluding certain ropes which apparently
maybe they're bonded together for all I know, maybe you use a
glue or something. But the the category that's being excluded is is
these hairs that are not even twisted together. And Nicholas's is twisted?
Yes, and then when it's twisted, that's okay. So we're including both,
so on the one hand we're including materials, and we're including even
if they're not woven, but at least they have to be twisted.
Yeah, they say something there about that? The notes over here that's
quoting Rashi saying when it talks about those measuring strings. Yes. They're
made of goat's hair that had not been spun, but merely twisted.
Oh, not spun but merely twisted? Let me check Rashi. I don't...
that's an interpretation. I don't see Rashi saying that. Rashi says ואינו
טווי, Ve'eino tavui, which is spun, ולא דמי לקולע שלשה נימין דלעיל
דהתם טווי הוא. Velo dami lekolei'a sheloshah nimin dile'eil dehatam tavui hu.
Yeah, but it's... yeah, he's comparing it... anyway, he doesn't say that
it is twisted. Maybe, maybe you're right, that would give make more
sense out of it, but before the Gemara says... okay, maybe, it
could be. The Gemara spoke about twisting the strings together.
So Rashi does say here that they're not spun. So it's possible.
It's possible. I don't see that exactly in Rashi, but it's possible.
So maybe that's difference about spun versus twisted. But again, before the
Gemara when it spoke about the necklace, spoke about twisting together. Maybe
their understanding that means twisted and spun. Okay, but anyway, somehow this
is not fully processed like normal types of fabric. It's either not
spun or not spun and twisted, something along those lines. The ropes
that are not tamei. Okay, so now the Gemara says like this:
Okay, so now we've learned out from O to include even other
hairs. So the Gemara says והא אפיקתיה, Veha afiktei, third wide line,
one minute, you use the O to include the ropes that are
tamei. So how can you say the O is including different types
of hair? So the Gemara says: No, הני מילי מקמי דליתי גזירה
שוה. Hanei milei mikami deleitei gezeirah shavah. Then we needed the O
before we had the big equal sign, before we made the
gezeirah shavah. Now we have the gezeirah shavah. So the gezeirah shavah
on the one hand by meis you have a very inclusive word
כל מעשה עזים. Kol ma'aseh izim. So כל מעשה עזים Kol ma'aseh
izim comes to tell us be very inclusive. You don't need the
O which we were using to inclusive. כל מעשה עזים Kol ma'aseh
izim tell us very inclusive. Sak puts a little bit of the
brakes on it. It has to be a little bit like sackcloth,
at least the strings have to be woven or twisted. But a
little bit it has to be like sack, but כל מעשה עזים
Kol ma'aseh izim is very inclusive, so you don't need the O
anymore since we're now putting the two parshiot together. So the O
comes to include even other hairs.
Just animal hair or is it literally those two? I presumably any
animal hair, but it's yeah it doesn't spell it out. So it
says השתא דאתי גזירה שוה. Hashta de'ati gezeirah shavah. Now we have
the big gezeirah shavah. So we have the inclusive word from כל
מעשה Kol ma'aseh and the limiting word from sak even though they're
in different parshiot, ייסר ליה, Yaysar lei, we have leftover the word
O to include other types of animal hairs. ואין לי אלא בשרץ.
Ve'ein li ela basheretz. Okay, but now we're back to I mean
going back to where we were before.
Now I know the word O includes other animal hairs by the
rodent. בטמא מת מנין? Betamei meis minayin? How do I know by
dead bodies? Of course the answer is obvious, you already made a
gezeirah shavah. You already made your gezeirah shavah, but the Gemara right
you have your big equal sign. So once you use the O
now to include other hairs, now we can apply to the dead
bodies. But before the Gemara gets there it's saying maybe you don't
need to learn it from gezeirah shavah, the Beraita. Maybe you can
learn it from you know logic, a kal vachomer, like Michael says.
והדין, Vehadin, it stands to reason, טימא במת וטימא בשרץ. Tima bemeis
vetima basheretz.
It says, you know, these types of... of garments are טמא by
corpses and by rodents. מה כשטימא בשרץ עשה דבר הבא מזנב סוס
וזנב בקר כמעשה עזים mah keshetamei besheretz asah davar haba mizanav sus
vezanav bakar kema'aseh izim when it's talking about rodents, it says that
stuff that comes from animals from horse hairs and cow hairs are
like goat hair and includes these types of hairs for the טומאה
tumah, of a שרץ. sheretz. And rodents are normally a more lenient
category, right? So here if it's including them by even the טומאה
tumah of rodents, אף כשטימא במת עשה דבר הבא מזנב סוס וזנב
בקר כמעשה עזים, af keshetamei bemeis asah davar haba mizanav sus vezanav
bakar kema'aseh izim,
it should treat stuff from cow hair and horse hair like goat
hair. So basically maybe we don't need גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. If
it's being strict by the שרצים sheratzim and saying either other animal
hairs are considered like garments, how much more so should it be
strict by corpses? So the גמרא Gemara says hang, yeah, is that
really true? אם הכי בטומאת ערב, im hach be'tumash erev, maybe it's
including, it's being more broad by things that are only טמא for
one day till the night, שהיא מרובה, shehi merubah, which is a
larger category, right? Most things are only one day טומאה. tumah You
know, it's a very tiny category of things that are seven days.
Dead bodies and certain types of טומאות that come from sort of
things that come out of the body. Okay, so if it's going
to broaden the category of objects that can become טמא by one
day, that's because one day is anyway a very broad category. So
נרבה בטומאת שבע, narbeh betumash shiva, will we also include, you know,
broaden the types of objects by seven day טומאה, tumah, שהיא מועטת,
shehi mu'etes, which is a smaller category? Now that's a little bit
of a funny, right? Because at the end of the day, מת
meis is much more stricter than the rodent. But you know, but
when you're making an argument by analogy or by
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you can pick holes, you can like, you
know, make holes in it. You can say it's not exactly the
same. Yes, I know שרצים are normally more lenient, but on the
other hand, they're more pervasive. So maybe if they're more pervasive, the
application should be more pervasive. So you cannot necessarily logically prove from
one to be the other. So again we go back to our
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah It's just making some מדרשי הלכה, midrashei halacha,
I should tell you by the way, that this is a classic
style of מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, you know, not just a ברייתא,
but like ספרא Sifra and ספרי, Sifrei, the מדרשי הלכה, midrashei halacha,
the תנאיים tannaic works on the פסוקים pzukim where they'll start by
saying, maybe I could learn it out this way, and try to
have a whole like argument for it and usually like maybe I
could learn it out logically? No, you could make this challenge, you
could show it's different this way and then they get back to
a more formal proof like a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. type of
a way of learning. It's interesting to know like what, why they
bother going through that process. One way is just helps to clarify
the, you know, the ways in which different categories are different, don't
lump everything together. The other point might also be, although you know,
this really needs to be thought more through, I'm just throwing this
off of the top of my head, that it's trying to show
the limits of human logic. You know, that you can't figure out
everything on your own just logically. We sometimes by logic we wouldn't
have got here, look, you need a פסוק. pusuk. So that's what
it's doing here. You even could not have applied from שרץ sheretz
to מת mais, even though שרץ sheretz is more lenient. So we
have to go back to our גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah תלמוד לומר
בגד ועור בגד ועור לגזירה שוה. talmud lomar beged vo-or beged vo-or
legezeirah shavah. נאמר בגד ועור בשרץ, ne'emar beged vo-or besheretz, it says
that phrase by the rodent. ונאמר בגד ועור במת, vene'emar beged vo-or
bemeis, it says it by the corpses. מה בגד ועור האמור בשרץ
עשה דבר הבא מזנב סוס וזנב בקר כמעשה עזים, mah beged vo-or
ha'amur besheretz asah davar haba mizanav sus vezanav bakar kema'aseh izim, the
same way by rodents it treats horse hair and cow hair like
goat hair and to be a type of material that could become
טמא when made into a garment, אף בגד ועור האמור במת, af
beged vo-or ha'amur bemeis, so similarly when it uses that phrase by
a corpse, עשה דבר הבא מזנב סוס וזנב בקר כמעשה עזים, asah
davar haba mizanav sus vezanav bakar kema'aseh izim, it makes it like,
you apply the same הלכה halacha that even things that come from
horse hair and cows hair are also like goat hair and can
become garments that can become טמא. Charlie, you had a question? You
covered it. Okay great. So the גמרא Gemara says ומופנה. umufne. Now
this גזירה שוה gezeirah shavahs. is open, right? Here's another principle which
we are about to see about גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah, You know,
a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah it can be, you know, it's a
dangerous tool. It's a very helpful tool in the right hands, but
it could be a dangerous tool in the wrong hands because you
know, if you can just make a big equal sign between things
that have the same phrase, you'll just start randomly applying one laws
to the other even though, you know, where does it end? So
the גמרא Gemara says sometimes can גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. be actually
sort of critiqued by a rational argument, critique. Like wait, you can't
make those two things equal, I mean they're so different. So here
the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between two different categories of a גזירה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. If the phrases are seen as extra, they didn't have
to be written there, and their whole purpose is to make the
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah And then it's like a very strong equal
sign and you can't use logic to critique it. The whole point
of it is to say, apply category A to B and B
to A. That's if the words are extra. If the words aren't
extra, they're functioning, they're needed in the פסוקים pzukim and you're just
trying to make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because you have similar
phrases, but the phrases are not superfluous, in that case you can
critique the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah by a, like a rational argument.
But it could still stand. Okay. It could still stand if you
have a response to the rational argument, but a rational argument could
challenge and undermine. So the גמרא Gemara here is saying because this
can be seriously challenged on a rational basis, we have to say
that these words בגד ועור beged ve-or are extra and allows to
make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah, that cannot be critiqued. Okay, and
that's what it says right now. מופנה, mufneh, these words are extra,
are open, open to be used. Okay, where are they?
דאי לאו מופנה, de'i lav mufneh, because if they weren't open, extra,
איכא למיפרך, ika le-mifra, then you could challenge
it like we said a minute ago.
מה לשרץ שכן מטמא בכעדשה. mah le-sheretz sheken metamei be-khadasheh. Right, once
you have גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, if you're going to challenge גזירה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, if all you have is an analogy, it's enough
to point out they're not exactly analogous. If you have גזירה שוה,
gezeirah shavah you start with a presumption that you're going to apply
one to the other and if you're going to critique it, you
need a strong critique. But here the גמרא Gemara, has a better
critique than it said before. There's ways in which rodents are more
strict than corpses. What is that? For a corpse to transmit טומאה,
it has to be a כזית, ke-zayis, the size of an olive.
For a rodent, it's enough that it's a size of a lentil
bean. So since we see there are ways in which the תורה
Torah says that rodents transmit טומאה in cases that dead bodies would
not, maybe the same is true by the garments and therefore just
because, you know, a horsehair works for rodents, doesn't mean it works
for dead bodies. So the גמרא Gemara says you could make that
critique. Therefore, and that's a really strong critique, and therefore if you
want the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah, to win, you have to say
not just that you have גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah. but that the
words are extra and it's ironclad and cannot be challenged. Okay. Who
said that makes rodents more strict though? Alright, no, but it means
that the תורה Torah says that there are cases where rodents transmit
טומאה where a מת mais in analogous case would not. And if
that's true, maybe it's true by the garments as well. It's not
far-fetched. So the גמרא Gemara says, לאיי אפנויי מופנה. le'ai afnuyei mufneh.
How can you say it's extra? מכדי שרץ איתקש לשכבת זרע. mikhtei
sheretz itkesh le-shikhvat zera. So here's how it's מופנה. mufneh. Because a
שרץ sheretz is compared to a semen that the same way semen
causes טומאה, שרץ sheretz does. דכתיב, de-khaktiv, it says in the פסוק,
pasuk, איש אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע, ish asher tetzei mimenu shikhvat
zera, if a man whose semen comes out from and he's טמא.
וסמיך ליה, ve-samikh lei, and then it says איש אשר יגע בכל
שרץ. ish asher yiga be-khol sheretz. If a man touches any rodent.
So the תורה Torah juxtaposed them and basically says they're similar. So
once we know it's similar to שכבת זרע, shikhvat zera, וכתיב ביה
בשכבת זרע, u-khthiv bei be-shikhvat zera, and it says by שכבת זרע,
shikhvat zera, וכל בגד וכל עור, ve-khol beged ve-khol or, that what
does שכבת זרע shikhvat zera make טמא? Any garment and any leather.
אשר יהיה עליו שכבת זרע, asher yihiyeh alav shikhvat zera, that the
semen is on, becomes טמא. So if you said it by שכבת
זרע, shikhvat zera, we should know of course it's true by rodents.
So בגד ועור דכתב רחמנא בשרץ למה לי? beged ve-or de-kathav rachamana
be-sheretz lama li? So why did the תורה Torah by the rodent
have to repeat בגד ועור? beged ve-or? So obviously it's an extra
phrase. שמע מינה לאפנויי, shema mina le-afnuyei, come tell me that it's
extra and because it's extra, you can use it for the גזירה
שוה. gezeirah shavah So the גמרא Gemara says ואכתי מופנה מצד אחד
הוא. ve-akhti mufneh mi-tzad echad hu.
But it's only extra on one direction, right? If you're comparing the
rodent to the dead body, so the rodent phrase is extra. But
the body phrase isn't extra. So when I told you it has
to be extra to make it beyond criticism, beyond critique, does one
of them have to be extra or do both phrases have to
be extra? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, הני ניחא למאן דאמר,
hani nicha le-man de-amar, that's fine according to the one that says
מופנה מצד אחד למדין ואין משיבין, mufneh mi-tzad echad lemedin ve-ein meshivin,
that even if only
phrases on one side of the pond is extra, you can make
your גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah, and you cannot critique it. אלא למאן
דאמר למדין ומשיבין, ella le-man de-amar lemedin u-meshivin, but there's an opinion
that says that if only one side of the phrases is extra,
you can make a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah yes, but משיבין, meshivin,
you also can critique it and if you have a good critique,
that will break it. So according to that approach, מה איכא למימר?
mai ika le-meimar? What can you say? Because you only have one
phrase extra and this can be critiqued. No, no, no, timeout. You'll
have your question in a minute. דמת נמי אפנויי מופנה. de-mais nami
afnuyei mufneh. The dead body also, the phrases by the corpse are
also extra phrases. Why is it extra by the corpse? מכדי, mikhtei,
same type of argument. מת איתקש לשכבת זרע. mais itkesh le-shikhvat zera.
The dead body is connected to the שכבת זרע. shikhvat zera. דכתיב,
de-khaktiv, והנוגע בכל טמא נפש, ve-ha-noge'ah be-khol tmei nefesh,
anybody that touches any person who is טמא because of corpse impurity,
או איש אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע, o ish asher tetzei mimenu
shikhvat zera, or someone from whom semen comes out from. וכתיב בשכבת
זרע וכל בגד וכל עור. u-khthiv be-shikhvat zera ve-khol beged ve-khol or.
And by שכבת זרע shikhvat zera it says garment or leather. So
basically again, we know the idea of garment or leather by מת,
mais, we could have learned it out from שכבת זרע shikhvat zera
because the תורה Torah compares them the same way it compares שכבת
זרע shikhvat zera to שרץ. sheretz. So בגד ועור דכתב רחמנא במת
למה לי? beged ve-or de-kathav rachamana be-mais lama li? So again, the
same way by שרץ sheretz בגד ועור beged ve-or is extra because
you could have learned it out from שכבת זרע, shikhvat zera, בגד
ועור beged ve-or is extra by מת because you could have learned
it out from שכבת זרע. shikhvat zera. So why does the תורה
Torah say it? שמע מינה לאפנויי. shema mina le-afnuyei. So both of
those phrases, both by שרץ sheretz and מת, it did not need
to say בגד ועור. beged ve-or. You could have learned it from
שכבת זרע. shikhvat zera. By both of them, each one of them
is extra, it's extra on both sides, allows you to make an
equal sign, make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. which is ironclad, cannot
be critiqued, and all of that is to tell you how now
we know that sackcloth is טמא even if it's not woven as
long as it's spun or twisted, but if it's not spun or
twisted at all or whatever, different questions exactly how much it's not
done at all, but anyway, then it's not טמא and that not
only goat hair but other animal hair. That's the whole point of
learning out these types of things that are טמא or not טמא,
which types of goat hair and what types of other animal hair.
But I think the more, you know, sort of interesting methodological point
is that it's sort of saying we couldn't have learned this all
out by logic. We needed a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah, So in
some degree it's showing the limits of the logic. On the other
hand, even גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah. says the גמרא, Gemara can itself
be critiqued by logic. So only very certain types of גזירות שוות
gezeirot shavot are applicable without and apply without any critique, but otherwise
there's this interesting, if you would, dialectic between logical derivations which sometimes
work, but if you're just doing it by analogy they're not as
strong, and then learning it from the פסוקים psukim which do work
but also they can be critiqued by logic unless you have a
very particular type of גזירה שוה. Yes. So, by the way, are
we saying also the מקרא מדרש לפניו ולא לאחוריו? mikra midrash l'fanav
v'lo l'achorov?
What? Because basically, the truth of the matter is, the פסוק pasuk
is מקיש לנפש m'kish l'nefesh but... yeah, next פסוק. pasuk.
No,
no, no, but if somebody טמא with, oh I see, so it's
separated by one. Yeah, I guess. All right, that's true. That raises
another question. How hard do you have to prove that the phrase
is extra? How rigorous does that proof have to be? All right,
yeah, I understand. All right, it faces a מדרש, Midrash, you know.
I got it. Okay, let's move on. So now the גמרא Gemara,
says, so all of that was about goat hair becoming טמא which
is all this derivation from discussing obviously different types of jewelry that
was טמא, etc. Now we go because we've introduced in part of
this the booty that they got from מדין, we're going to look
at those פסוקים. psukim. And that's interesting not just because it's a
source of certain things becoming טמא which directly connects, but also because
it talks about women's jewelry which is part of the theme of
what we've been talking about, which is, you know, women's jewelry. So
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara does with
this. ונקריב את קרבן ה' איש אשר מצא כלי זהב. V'nakriv es
korban Hashem ish asher matza kli zahav. So the נשיאים nesi'im come
and they say after all of the, you know, they were sort
of taxed to give a certain amount of the booty to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or whatever. But then afterwards the נשיאים nesi'im
come and say look, we just did a counting ולא נפקד ממנו
איש, v'lo nifkad mimenu ish, nobody was, our full troops came back,
nobody was killed in battle, so we bring in this gift to
God ונקריב את קרבן ה' v'nakriv es korban Hashem and it lists
all this type of jewelry that they had taken in battle that
they're giving it now as a gift to God.
ונקריב את קרבן ה' איש אשר מצא כלי זהב אצעדה וצמיד טבעת
עגיל וכומז, V'nakriv es korban Hashem ish asher matza kli zahav etz'ada
v'tzamid taba'at agil v'chumaz, all these different types of jewelry. אמר ר'
אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, so now we're going to try to identify
some of them. עגיל זה דפוס של דדין. Agil zeh d'fus shel
dadin. An עגיל agil is some type of a thing that was
worn like as a, as a form over the breasts for women.
So some type of a thing worn directly on the body.
כומז זה דפוס של בית הרחם. Kumaz zeh d'fus shel beis harechem.
And כומז, kumaz, that is some type of a form or some
type of an ornament that was worn right in the pubic area.
So אמר רב יוסף, אי הכי, Amar Rav Yosef ei hachi, so
both of them obviously are done, you know, in a very type
of sexual context and presumably it's worn directly against the body, not
outside on the clothing.
You know, like nowadays, I mean if that sounds weird, I mean
look nowadays, apparently people are getting piercings all over their bodies and
on, you know, very private parts of their bodies. So this is
something like that, that there would be this jewelry that would be
right on the private parts of their bodies. So אמר רב יוסף
Amar Rav Yosef, אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's what כומז kumaz
means, now I
understand היינו דמתרגמינן, hainu d'metargminan, that's how come the Aramaic translation is
מחוך. machoach. That's the translation of כומז, kumaz, מחוך. machoach. Which what
does מחוך machoach mean? But apparently he connects it to the word
גיחוך, gichuch, to laugh. דבר המביא לידי גיחוך. Davar hameivi lidei gichuch.
It brings to laughing. I'm not exactly sure why laughing, but maybe
they're, maybe they're laughing about it. Right, maybe רש"י Rashi says ליצנות,
leitzanut, like levity, like licentiousness. Okay, although I'm not, you know, maybe
that's like, you know, what the מדרש Midrash about when it says
that what's his name? That ישמעאל Yishmael was מצחק metzacheik and uses
it to speak about sort of a type of licentiousness. So אמר
ליה
רבה, Amar lei Rabbah, מגופיה דקרא שמע מינה. migufia d'kra shma mina.
You can figure this out from the פסוק pasuk itself.
כומז, Kumaz, the word כומז kumaz is like an acronym of כאן
מקום זימה. kan makom zimah. Here is the place of licentiousness. Okay,
so again, not saying that sex is always bad, but this type
of thing presumably is used in a very licentious manner, you know,
putting these type of jewelries directly on the... in the pubic region.
ויקצף משה, Vayiktzof Moshe, so now moving on, משה Moshe got angry
על פקודי החיל. al pekudei hachayil. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה, אמר להן משה לישראל, Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah Bar Avuha
amar lahen Moshe l'Yisrael, משה Moshe said, so he got angry to
them. Now he got angry not when they were bringing this thing,
that was later in the narrative. He got angry when they came
right back from the war when he saw that all of the
women were still alive. Okay, all of the women from מדין. So
he says, you know, they were with בני ישראל, Bnei Israel, they
were the reasons why בני ישראל Bnei Israel sinned. What did you
do keeping them alive? So אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה
Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah Bar Avuha, אמר להן משה לישראל, amar
lahen Moshe l'Yisrael, משה Moshe said
ישראל: Israel: שמא חזרתם לקלקולכם? Shema chazartem l'kilkulchem? Now I'm going to
read this the מהרש"א's Maharsha way which is much more פשט pshat
than רש"י's Rashi, way. Maybe you have returned to your bad ways,
like they're interested in, you know, sleeping, having sex with these women,
which is exactly what caused the sin. That's why you allowed these
women to be alive. לקלקולכם הראשון, L'kilkulchem harishon, your original bad ways.
אמרו לו לא נפקד ממנו איש. Amru lo lo nifkad mimenu ish.
Now we're jumping 50 פסוקים psukim later. Okay, so immediately משה Moshe
said you know you have to kill out the women. But we're
seeing that now when they come with their קרבן, korban, they're reflecting
back on the original accusation that משה Moshe made to them when
they first returned. They first returned, the women were alive, משה Moshe
said oh my god, you know, I got so angry. So implicitly
he's saying are you planning on sleeping with them? Are you going
back to your original sins? So jump 50 פסוקים psukim later and
they bring this קרבן korban
and now they're addressing his accusations. So it says like this, לא
נפקד ממנו איש, lo nifkad mimenu ish, nobody was lacking. So אמר
להם, amar lahem, which means everybody was very פרום. frum. Nobody strayed
from the good Jewish way that no, nobody, we haven't been sleeping
with these women. So אמר להן אם כן כפרה למה? amar lahen
im ken kapara lama? So why are you bringing this קרבן השם
korban Hashem לכפר על נפשותינו? l'chaper al nafshoteinu? What do you need
כפרה kapara for if you've been so פרום? frum? So אמרו לו
אם מידי עבירה יצאנו, amru lo im midei aveira yatzanu, maybe we
didn't actually act, we didn't actually have sex. מידי הרהור לא יצאנו.
midei hirhur lo yatzanu. מידי הרהור לא יצאנו, midei hirhur lo yatzanu,
but we did not, you know, we were not so פרום frum
that we did not have sexual thoughts. So therefore we're bringing this
to atone for sexual thoughts. So that's very interesting in general which
I'm not going to discuss now, you know, the גמרא's gemara. attitude
towards
הרהור hirhur and, you know, how, to what degree can somebody control
their types of, you know, their thoughts? And why is the גמרא
gemara so concerned with הרהור? hirhur? Is it concerned with it because
it leads to שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, it leads to like זרע
לבטלה, zera l'vatala, you know, to
seminal
emission and to masturbation? Or is it concerned that it per se
is evil to be having these thoughts? But that's at least, that's
clearly a theme in the גמרא gemara and that's what it's saying.
That's why we didn't actually sin but we had those thoughts. So
מיד
ונקרב את קרבן השם. miyad v'nakrev et korban Hashem. So they brought,
so we have brought forth God's sacrifice, this offering to God. תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'vei Rebbi Yishmael, the תנא Tanna of the
house of רבי ישמעאל. Rebbi Yishmael. מפני מה הוצרכו ישראל שבאותו הדור
כפרה? Mipnei ma hutzrechu Yisrael sheba'oto hador kapara? Why did they need
atonement? מפני שזנו עיניהם מן הערוה, Mipnei shezanu eineihem min ha'erva, because
their eyes זנו. zanu. Now very strange, רש"י, Rashi you would think
it's זנות. znut. רש"י Rashi says לשון מזון, lashon mazon, שנתנו במראית
העין, shenitnu b'marit ha'ayin, like they feasted on the ערוה, erva, which
is also an interesting way, right? You know, their eyes feasted on
the,
you know, on either literally the nakedness or the sexual seduction of
these women and so on. But מהרש"א Maharsha just says simply means
זנות. znut. It's like that they actually, you know, as it were,
fornicated visually. Okay, so that's why they, that's why they are being
punished. אמר רב ששת מפני מה מנה הכתוב תכשיטין שבחוץ עם תכשיטין
שבפנים? Amar Rav Sheshet mipnei ma mana hakatuv tachshitin shebachutz im tachshitin
shebifnim? Why did it put them all on the same list? It
says, you know, it lets טבעת, tabaat, which is a ring finger,
together with these things which are right on their, you know, which
are right on their body and
in the genital area. So why is it putting them all on
the same list? לומר לך כל המסתכל באצבע קטנה של אשה כאילו
מסתכל במקום התורפה, Lomar lach kol hamistakel b'etzba ktana shel isha k'ilu
mistakel b'makom hatorfa, that if anybody, meaning any man, looks sexually at
a woman, like did this type of thing זנו עיניהם, zanu eineihem,
sort of like a
lustful leer, sexual look, so it doesn't matter what part of the
woman he's looking at. Whether it's looking at a finger, whether he's
looking directly
at the naked area. Either way, it's inappropriate. It's looking at a
woman in a sexual way which for us we would talk about
in
from a feminist
perspective that it's the male gaze and it's objectifying women
and that problem. For the גמרא, gemara, it has a similar concern
about the male gaze, but for a different reason. Because it's about
הרהור hirhur and you should not be going around and doing these
types of lookings that constantly are provoking the יצר הרע yeitzer hara
and the lust and הרהור. hirhur. Okay, so that's why it's all
listed together because we're framing that the reason they're bringing this jewelry
is as a כפרה kapara for their gaze and for their הרהור
hirhur that resulted as part of, you know, according to הלכה halakha
there are some parts obviously that women have to cover but not
everything. I mean we don't say have to cover their fingers. I
know. Well, I wrote extensively about this about a half a year
ago and the גמרא gemara. is... It's not saying that this has
to be covered. Exactly. It's talking about the man's responsibility of how
he is looking and that's the point of the גמרא. Gemara And
all this jewelry, they were melting it down? Yeah, presumably they melted
it down and they used it in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
yeah. To take, it's like עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. What's not עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, I mean it is a good question. It sounds
to me like they... Maybe that's true, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say that, the גמרא Gemara seems to see it as more direct
about sexual seduction, but it does raise interesting questions about are there
limits on what can be used for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
in terms of how the stuff was used in the past. And
there are גמרות gemaras that do discuss that, about even if it's
not technical עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, if it was associated with it,
maybe it's inappropriate to be used. It could also be that the
melting down changes its identity. If it was real עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara that might be different. But if it's just a question about
like
its context in which it's been in, so a real transformation of
melting it down might be enough to change it. It's a good
point and it is discussed elsewhere. יעקב. Yaakov. Right. That's true, יעקב
Yaakov just had all that jewelry, he buried it, and he did
melt it down. Right. It's an interesting point, but that might have
been real עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So real עבודה זרה Avoda Zara
remains אסור assur even in a changed form. Okay, but עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara has to be burnt and completely destroyed and even in
changed form, you can't burn certain metals unless you got a really
hot fire anyway. Alright, but that's a very good point, but this
probably we're not saying is direct עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and therefore
have possibly different parameters. Alright, now we go on. יוצאת אשה בחוטי
שער. Yotze isha bechutei sear. Now we had all the list of
things you can't do, can't do rabbinically, can't do biblically. Now we're
talking about the things that you can do. A woman can go
out בחוטי שער bechutei sear with hair, not her own hair but
cut hair that now has been woven into her hair. בין משלה
בין משל חברתה, Bein mishela bein mishel chavertah, whether it's her hair
or whether her own cut hair that now she is weaving back
as a wig or some type of a thing, or whether it's
somebody else's hair that she's wearing, either strings within her own hair
or what a wig we'll actually get to, but she has other
hair woven into hers, that's fine. We're not afraid that she'll take
it off to show. And if you remember way back at the
beginning of the פרק, perek, our concern was she'll take it off,
certain things off to go to the מקווה, mikva, but hair is
not a חציצה chatzitza and therefore we're not concerned about that. I
was assuming her head was not covered. Well, that's a good question.
It's a good question. Maybe it could be an unmarried, maybe it
could be
the part, the little part that came out of the covering. Actually
the משנה mishna very much assumed it was covered because it wasn't
concerned about taking off the hat because you wouldn't take off your
hat in public, you'd have to keep your hair covered. So it's
a good question. Maybe this was all under the hat, although one
wonders why you're bothering if it's all under there. So maybe it's
the part of the hair that comes outside of the hat.
So but that's a very good point. Okay. בבהמה, Beheima, whether it's
animal hair. ובטוטפת Ub’totefet
with a type of a head ornament, טוטפת totafet like טוטפות. totafot.
ובסרביטין Ub’sarvitin and with בסרביטין, sarvitin, which we will see what, discuss
that in the גמרא, Gemara, actually we discussed that earlier what the
בסרביטין sarvitin was, I'm just not remembering exactly. Bangles. Bangles, what's the
bangle?
Okay. בזמן שהן, Bizman shehein, בזמן שהן bizman shehein תפורין בכבול, tefurin
bekav, when they are woven into her head covering, into her cap.
Because if they're woven into her hat, she won't take them off
because she would have to take her hat off and we're obviously
she's not gonna take her hat off in public. So that's okay
as long as they're woven into the hat. בכבול ובפאה נכרית, Bekavul
ub’pea nachrit, now she can wear a בכבול kavul which is some
type of a like a scarf underneath her hat, underneath her like
hairnet, or a פאה נכרית pea nachrit which is a wig, okay?
So she could wear these לחצר lachatzer into the courtyard, maybe she
can't wear it into the רשות הרבים reshus harabim but at least
she can wear it into the courtyard. Well, we'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara, במוך שבבאזנה
ובמוך שבסנדלה ובמוך שהתקינה לנידתה, Bemoch shebe’ozna uvemoch shebesandala uvemoch shehitkina lenidatah,
now she can wear a certain type of a like a folded
cloth in her ear if she's got some type of an ear
infection or put it in her sandal to stop her from getting
a callus on her foot, or
she has it as a type of a sanitary napkin because she's
menstruating. She can wear all of these things. Now רש"י Rashi says,
why does she have it for as a sanitary napkin? רש"י Rashi
says to prevent her garments from getting dirty. But תוספות Tosfos says,
reminds us of an earlier סוגיא sugia that says if it's something
to protect the garment and not to protect the body, it's not
considered clothing. So תוספות Tosfos. says no, it's obviously that she doesn't
want to bleed and then get on her body, so then it's
coming to protect herself and then it's okay. And all these other
things are obviously directly to serve the body, to protect her foot,
to help her ear and so on.
בפלפל ובגלגל ובסלע גרגיר מלח, Be’pilpel uve’galgal u’vesela gargar melach, she can
also have pepper or salt in her mouth, maybe as some type
of a thing for bad breath or whatever, we'll see. וכל דבר
שניתן לתוך פיה, Vechol davar shenittan letoch piha, anything that she puts
in her mouth is okay, presumably if it's, well we'll see, meaning
not if it's done as a way like you can't put your
house key in your mouth, you can't still carry in your mouth,
but it means things that are done for this type of reason,
let's say presumably for bad breath, ובלבד שלא תתן לכתחילה בשבת. uvilvad
shelo titten l'chatchila b'Shabbos. שבת. Shabbos Don't put it on שבת Shabbos;
itself. Meaning,
don't on שבת; Shabbos, if you had it in your mouth from
before שבת, Shabbos it's okay. Now, let me just ובין שנפל, u'vein
shenafal, and if you had it from before שבת Shabbat? and fell
out, לא תחזיר, lo tachzir, don't put it back. Now, what's the
whole problem of putting it in your mouth on שבת? Shabbos. So,
תוספות Tosfos has two explanations. One is, it's like taking medicine on
שבת. Shabbos If you're doing it for bad breath, it's like taking
a רפואה refuah on שבת Shabbos and that's the problem.
To which he says, no, if that were true though then you'd
be allowed to put it back, because if you started if you
had some medicine on you from before שבת Shabbos and it fell
off, he actually tries to prove from elsewhere you're allowed to put
it back. So תוספות Tosafos, says the problem isn't medicine, the problem
is that people will think you're using this not as a type
of medicinal thing. If they see you putting something in your mouth
on שבת Shabbos, and then walking out, they'll think you're just trying
to find a sneaky way to carry things. What do you think
you're trying to? Maybe, I don't know. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafos says
it's a concern that it looks like a sneaky way of carrying
things, but the other read is that it's a concern about medicinal,
which raises interesting questions: if you're not allowed to take certain medicines
on שבת, Shabbos. how do we treat about things that are for
bad breath, mouthwash and whatnot? Is that a medicine or not a
medicine? So anyway, a little bit that's what's going on here, the
two explanations of תוספות. Tosafos. Yeah, we have yet to actually look
at the real סוגיא sugya about medicines on שבת. Shabbos. Anyway, it
says שן תותבת, shen toteves, now she can also wear a false
tooth. But שן של זהב, shen shel zahav, if it's a golden
tooth, רבי מתיר וחכמים אוסרים. Rebbi matir v'Chachamim osrin. רבי Rebbi says
it's okay, the rabbis say no because of course if it's a
golden tooth, then she'll want to take it out and show her
friends in the middle of the street. That might be a little
bit scary.
Apparently, that's what now you understand why רבי Rebbi may or רבי
Rebbi says it's okay. All right, so we're going to look at
all this, but let's start first things first. Wait, is this the
gold one, but let's say it's made out of something? No, only
the gold one, it's a concern. Okay, וצריכה, u'tzricha, you need to
tell me all of the cases of the different types of hair.
דאי אשמעינן דידה, dei ashmi'enan didah, if it just said her hair
is okay, woven into cut hair woven into her hair, משום דלא
מאיס, mishum d'lo ma'is, that that's not a disgusting thing to wear,
that would be very natural. אבל חברתה דמאיס, aval chavertah d'ma'is, her
friend's hair, which maybe is considered disgusting—if it's disgusting I don't know
why you're doing it, but maybe it means that maybe other people
will think it's inappropriate—אימא לא, eima lo,
maybe not, maybe we're afraid that she'll be embarrassed and certain people
will see this other foreign hair and she'll take it out and
walk with it in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. ואי אשמעינן דחברתה, v'ei
ashmi'enan dechavertah,
if it said her friend's hair, fine, דמינה איהו, d'minah ihu, that's
because at least it's human hair, it's from the same species. אבל
דבהמה, aval d'beheimah, animal hair, לאו מינה איהו, lav minah ihu, that's
not the same species, and therefore maybe then she'll be embarrassed and
if in certain contexts—again, if she's really embarrassed, why is she doing
it? But okay, it means that at least in some contexts maybe
she'll be embarrassed and then אימא לא, eima lo, maybe she can't
wear it because she might come to take it off—צריכה, tzricha, it
has to tell me all three cases. Come to take it off
so that for closer inspection if you feel on your head then
maybe nobody will notice so? No, but then the opposite. Why can't
you wear it on your head because we're afraid you'll take it
off. So why are we afraid you'll take it off? Only if
it's your own hair or possibly a human hair. But if it's
animal hair, then you would? You would not, but the גמרא Gemara
is saying the opposite, that the animal hair I think that there's
more of a concern you'll come to it will be a problem.
So okay, you'll take it off when you see your friends coming.
That's what I'm saying, that to some degree you would wear this
for certain functional purposes, but in certain social contexts it would have
been seen as embarrassing or inappropriate and you might come to take
it off. Okay, תנא, tana, ובלבד שלא תצא ילדה בשל זקנה וזקנה
בשל ילדה. u'vilvad shelo teitzei yaldah b'shel zekeinah u'zekeinah b'shel yaldah. A
young woman cannot wear an old woman's hair like the white hair
woven into her young dark hair would look inappropriate and we're afraid
she'll take it off, and similarly an old woman cannot wear a
young woman's hair woven into hers because also it's very different types
of hair colors, one is white and one is gray and one
is a different color, and therefore we're afraid she'll come to take
it off. You mean like a brunette and you wear? All right,
בשלמא זקנה בשל ילדה שבח הוא לה, bishlama zekeinah b'shel yaldah shevach
hu lah, so I understand an old woman wearing a young woman's
hair, that's something that looks very nice, she's trying to get some
nice dark hair into her hair. So therefore what? So therefore maybe
it means that she'll come to show her friends, she'll say look
at this lovely hair I have woven in, so I understand that
concern.
אלא
ילדה בשל זקנה אמאי, ela yaldah b'shel zekeinah amai, a young
woman wearing an old woman's hair—why? Now why what? It could be
like why is she bothering to do it, what's the concern? גנאי
הוא לה, gnai hu lah, it's something that doesn't look attractive on
her. So that's one thing, like why would I even be concerned
she would do it? The other possible explanation רש"י Rashi to תוספות
Tosafos says
is that why do you even need to tell me that it's
a problem? Certainly it's going to be so embarrassing, of course she'll
come to take it off if she sees her friends, you don't
even have to tell me it. So the גמרא says fine, איידי
דתני זקנה בשל ילדה תנא נמי ילדה בשל זקנה. aidi d'tani zekeinah
b'shel yaldah tana nami yaldah b'shel zekeinah. You told me one, you
told me the other, one of them is obvious that we're afraid
she'll take it off. But wearing the young woman's hair is not
so obvious and you have to tell me even there we have
that concern. Okay, וכבולה בפאה נכרית וחצר. u'chevulah b'peiah nochris v'chatzer. And
this is the conversation I really want to focus on, at least
for a few minutes. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so you can wear
these types of things into the courtyard, into the courtyard, but not
in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So אמר רב Amar Rav says רב,
Rav, כל שאסרו חכמים לצאת בו לרשות הרבים אסור לצאת בו לחצר,
Kol she'asru chachamim latzeis bo lereshus harabim asur latzeis bo lachatzer, in
that
everything we've been talking until this משנה Mishna that you can't wear
in the public domain, all these jewelry, you can't even wear in
your courtyard. Why? Because you wear it in your courtyard, you'll come
to step out of your courtyard and go into your public domain.
And רש"י Rashi says it's even a courtyard with an עירוב. Eruv.
You can't wear it because we're so afraid you'll come to walk
out into the street. That's what he says. חוץ מכבולה ופאה נכרית,
Chutz mikvula upeiah nochris,
the only thing they allowed is the כבולה kvula and the פאה
נכרית peiah nochris mentioned here in the משנה. Mishna. And we'll see
why in a minute. רבי ענני בר ששון משמיה דרבי ישמעאל אמר,
Rabbi Anani bar Sasson mishmei deRabbi Yishmael amar, רבי ענני בר ששון
Rabbi Anani bar Sasson says in the name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yose, הכל ככבולה. Hakol
kikvula.
Everything is allowed in the courtyard, all the things you can't wear,
it's all allowed in the courtyard. תנן, Tnan, our, let's take a
look. Our משנה Mishna says בכבולה ובפאה נכרית לחצר, bikvula uvefeiah nochrit
lachatzer,
that you can go out to the כבולה kvula and the פאה
נכרית peiah nochris in the חצר, chatzer, and in an earlier משנה
Mishna it says you can't go out with them. בשלמא לרב ניחא,
Bishlama l'Rav nicha, for
רב Rav it makes sense. When an earlier משנה Mishna says you
can't go out, it means you can't go out at all, and
then says oh, but you can go in a חצר, chatzer, which
means normally when it says you can't go out, it even means
you can't go out in a חצר. chatzer. These are the two
things that we're saying you can go out in a חצר, chatzer,
but normally everything else we've been saying you can't go out means
you can't go out at all, even in a חצר. chatzer. That
works very good according to רב. Rav. אלא רבי ענני בר ששון
קשיא, Ela Rabbi Anani bar Sasson kashya, for him it's difficult, because
if can't go out before just meant רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim and
חצר chatzer was okay, you wouldn't have to say you can go
out with the חצר, chatzer, that's taken for granted, and it should
be true by everything. So the גמרא says רבי ענני בר ששון
משמיה דמאן תמרה לה, Rabbi Anani bar Sasson mishmei deman tamreilah, one
minute, who's he saying this teaching in the name of? משמיה דרבי
ישמעאל, Mishmei deRabbi Yishmael, in the name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yose, in the name of
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yose. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
תנא הוא ופליג, Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yose tanna hu ufalig, רבי ישמעאל
ברבי
יוסי Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yose is a תנא tanna and he argues.
You're right, it's not our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna says only
two things in a חצר, chatzer, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael
berabbi Yose says anything you can wear in a חצר. chatzer. ורב,
Verav, and according to רב, Rav, מאי שנא הני, mai shna hani,
what makes these special and different that these we're allowing and other
things we're not? אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, said עולא, Ulla, כדי שלא
תתגנה על בעלה. kedei shelo titganei al ba'ala. We have to let
her wear something in order, you know, outside of the, you know,
outside of the house, so that she should not be, you know,
unattractive to her husband. How we know that this is a value?
כדתניא והדוה בנדתה, Keditanya vehadavah benidatah, when a woman flows in her
נדה niddah period. זקנים הראשונים אמרו, Zekeinim harishonim amru,
originally the sages said שלא תכחול ולא תפקוס ולא תתקשט. shelo tichol
velo tifkos velo tiskasheit.
She shouldn't put on eye shadow or rouge or any other types
of
jewelry. בבגדי צבעונין Bevigdee tivonim and not wear excuse me, colored garments.
עד שבא רבי עקיבא
ולימד, Ad sheba Rabbi Akiva velimeid, until רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said
אם כן אתה מגנה על בעלה, im kein ata megana al ba'ala,
then you will make her of her, you know, disgusting to her
husband, ונמצא בעלה מגרשה, venimtsa ba'ala megarshei, and the husband will divorce
her. אלא מה תלמוד לומר והדוה בנדתה, Ela ma talmud lomar vehadavah
benidatah, so what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? It doesn't mean that
you're supposed to totally make her disgusting, that she should be treated
as disgusting. בנדתה תהא עד שתבא במים, Benidatah tehei ad shetavo bemayim,
it just means she has that status of being a נדה niddah
until she goes to the מקוה, mikva, but you should not learn
from that anything else. What does it mean? So what were they
learning from it? Apparently they were learning the word נדה niddah can
mean flow, but the word נדה niddah can also be associated with
the word like נידוי, niddui, and somebody rejected and cast out. So
it seems like they were learning that part of the idea of
status of being a נדה niddah is somebody, a woman who has
to be cast out and cast away and somebody very, you know,
sort of all, you know, this whole taboo. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is saying no, I'm sorry. It's just a הלכה halacha that
she's until she goes to the מקוה. mikvah. There's no idea value
of making her disgusting for and also it's actually contrary because it
will, you know, make the husband want to divorce her, especially if
it's a regular thing that happens. So you see that there's this
concern about trying to make sure that that's not, that we do
not get so quote-unquote פרום frum that we lead to real issues
about שלום בית shalom bayis and relationships. It's also worth noting that
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, of course, had a very romantic relationship with
his wife and maybe is much more sensitive to these issues. So
anyway, that's why you see it's a value. So now I just
want to say because in the last few minutes and we really
have a few more lines to read to fully end this discussion,
but before we do I want to just talk about the הלכה
halacha here. Because as Ari was asking us when we started this,
if you can't wear it in a חצר, chatzer, so nowadays even
if we have an עירוב, Eruv, how can you wear this stuff,
right? So take, so if you look at תוספות, Tosfos תוספות Tosfos
says רב ענני בר ששון אמר הכל ככבולה, Rav Anani bar Sasson
amar hakol kikvula, נראה דהלכה כרב ענני. nira dehalacha kerav Anani. So
we rule like him, that it's allowed in a חצר. chatzer. דאמרי
מילתא משמיה דרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Damri milsa mishmei deRabbi Yishmael berabbi
Yose, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael תנא הוא ופליג, tanna hu ufalig, ועוד
דבסופי הלכה להקל. veod devesofei halacha lehakil. We should be lenient, this
is all דרבנן, derabanan, and you can wear it in a חצר.
chatzer. And I'm first reading תוספות. Tosfos, ורב ענני דמשרי בחצר, VeRav
Anani demashrei bechatzer, now when רש"י Rashi says we're talking about a
courtyard, רש"י Rashi, says we're talking about a courtyard with an עירוב.
Eruv. תוספות says no, we're talking about even a courtyard without an
עירוב. Eruv. He's allowing a courtyard,
היינו אפילו... hainu afilu... So now, okay, if you put that all
together, we rule like him and you can wear it in a
non-עירוב Eruv courtyard, so at least you shouldn't be able to wear
it in a רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, that's what we've been seeing
from the beginning of the מסכתא. Masecheta. But now we're going to
see why תוספות has been pushing to take the lenient approach. We
should rule it's allowed in a חצר chatzer and even a חצר
chatzer without an עירוב, Eruv, because basically he's about to tell us
that in his days, women wore all this jewelry out in the
street and basically this entire פרק Perek was ignored. Okay, so he
says,
אם כן נשים מותרות להתקשט בבית ובחצר ובטבעת ובתכשיטין. im kein nashim
mutaros lehiska'sheish bevayis uvachatzer uvetaba'as uvetachshitin. So therefore, women can wear all
this stuff. And how about רשות הרבים? Reshus HaRabim? That's also not
a problem. ואנו שאין לנו רשות הרבים גמור. ve-anu she-ein lanu reshus
harabim gomur. We don't have a real רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim nowadays.
This is what allows all עירובים, Eruvin, an assumption that we don't
have a רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. שכל רשות הרבים שלנו כרמלית היא.
she-kol reshus harabim shelanu karmelis hi. All of our רשות הרבים Reshus
HaRabims are really just a כרמלית. Karmelis. Why? Why isn't it a
real רשות הרבים? Reshus HaRabim? שהרי אין מבוי שלנו רחוב שאינו י"ח
אמה. she-harei ein mavoi shelanu rachov she-eino yod ches ama. Right, it's
not 16 אמות amos wide, ours certainly
aren't, ולא ששים רבוא בוקעים בו, ve-lo shishim ribo boke'im bo, which
is a new criteria the גאונים Geonim came up with. There isn't
600,000 people that travel on it. So we don't have a real
רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. Everything is a כרמלית. Karmelis. We're going to
rule that this is all מותר muttar in a כרמלית. Karmelis. So
everything is מותר. muttar. הרי כחצר שאינה מעורבת ומותרת ומותרת נשים שלנו
להתקשט בטבעות ובתכשיטין כן פירש רבנו תם. harei ke-chatzer she-eina me'ureves u-muteres
u-muteres nashim shelanu lehiska'sheish be-taba'os u-ve-tachshitin kein peirush Rabbeinu Tam. That's what
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says. A classic רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, that
you have a common practice that's in- seems to be flouting the
whole גמרא, the entire פרק Perek we learned, figures out a way
to make it מותר. muttar. We rule like the opinion חצר, chatzer,
we say it's a חצר chatzer even without an עירוב, Eruv, and
we say nowadays everything we have is a חצר chatzer without an
עירוב. Eruv. Okay, that's what רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says. Just for
one minute if you look at the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, I
just want to show you, okay, the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch here
brings down a whole range of opinions. He says כל שאסרו חכמים
לצאת לרשות הרבים אסור לצאת לחצר שאינה מעורבת. kol she-asru chachamim latzeis
le-reshus harabim asur latzeis le-chatzer she-eina me'ureves. You can't go out to
a חצר chatzer without an עירוב. Eruv. And then he says, some
say you can't even, רש"י, Rashi, he says רש"י, Rashi but I'll
skip the second opinion. You can't even go out into a חצר
chatzer with an עירוב. Eruv. That's רש"י's read. And then he says,
third opinion, ויש אומרים שהכל מותר לצאת בו בחצר אפילו אינה מעורבת,
ve-yeish omrim she-ha-kol muttar latzeis bo be-chatzer afilu eina me'ureves, which is
תוספות's read of the opinion here of רב ענני, Rav Anani, which
is that you can at least go out to- you can go
out to a חצר chatzer even without an עירוב. Eruv. והאידנא נשי
דידן נהגו לצאת בטבעות ובתכשיטין. ve-ha-idna nashi didan nahagu latzeis be-taba'os u-ve-tachshitin.
Women wear all the jewelry, basically the entire פרק Perek is forgotten.
Now he gives three reasons why. א, A, I've obviously א ב
ג A B C here,
ויש אמרו דמדינא אסורות. ve-yeish amru de-midina asuros. Really it is אסור
assur for them. אלא שכיון שלא ישמעו מוטב יהיו שוגגות. ella she-keivan
she-lo yishme'u mutav yihyu shogegos. They're not going to listen, it's only
Rabbinic, so better just leave them be. That's answer number one, not
the best answer. ב, ויש ללמד עליהם זכות לומר שנהגו כן על
פי סברא אחרונה שכתבתי. ve-yeish le-lammed aleihem zachus lomar she-nahagu kein al
pi sevara achrona she-katavti. The last explanation, that it's all a חצר
שאינה מעורבת chatzer she'eina me'ureves and השתא דלית לנו רשות הרבים גמור,
ve-hashta de-leis lanu reshus harabim gamur, everything is a חצר שאינה מעורבת.
chatzer eina me'ureves. תוספות, okay?
It's all a כרמלית, Karmelis, they're allowed to wear it in a
כרמלית, Karmelis, it's all מותר. muttar. And then the רמ"א Rema adds
a third opinion. ויש אומרים עוד טעם להתיר דעכשיו ששכיחי תכשיטין. ve-yeish
omrim od ta'am le-hattir de-achshav she-shchichi tachshitin. This is fascinating because it
goes to questions you've all been asking. שכיחי תכשיטין, shchichi tachshitin, it's
very common to wear jewelry even during the weekday. ויוצאים אפילו בחול.
ve-yotzim afilu be-chol. And therefore what? וליכא למיחש דילמא שלפה ומחויא. ve-leika
le-michash dilma shalfa u-machvya.
There's no longer the concern that they'll take it off to show
their friends. Our sociological realities have changed and people are not taking
off their jewelry in the middle of the street. כמו בימיהם שלא
היו רגילים לצאת בהם רק בשבת. kemo be-yameihem she-lo hayu regilim latzeis
bahem rak be-Shabbos.
So in their days they would only wear on שבת. Oh my
god, I've never seen that before, here let me show you. Nowadays
it's very common, nobody takes off their jewelry in the middle of
the street, which is amazing because this is the question about how
much does changing sociological realities change the parameters of the תקנה. Takana.
So until now all the arguments have been no, we פוסקים posken
in a certain way but we're following the דין din of the
גמרא, it's just that everything now is a כרמלית Karmelis and it's
okay in a כרמלית. Karmelis. This answer is actually the whole פרק
Perek changed because our sociological realities have changed. And since women don't
take it off, all of these things that you're not allowed are
only in a context where there's a concern they'll be taken off,
but when there's not that concern, that's allowed. And then the שלחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch just ends by saying that's for the דרבננים. de-rabanans.
But things that the גמרא says is a דאורייתא de-Oraisa concern is
considered carrying and not jewelry and not clothing, that obviously still remains
an issue. But basically here we see that the entire פרק Perek
that we've been learning in practice was completely ignored. People wore their
jewelry in the street and whatever, and we basically argue either the
sociological realities have changed or it's all a כרמלית Karmelis and we
rule that in a כרמלית Karmelis it's okay. Okay, yeah. Well I'm
just- we'll just end then you'll ask your question in a second.
You go ahead.